<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>EconomyNext</title>
	<atom:link href="https://economynext.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://economynext.com</link>
	<description>EconomyNext</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 06:34:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://economynext.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/cropped-fev-32x32.png</url>
	<title>EconomyNext</title>
	<link>https://economynext.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka government deposits Rs1.1trillion in state banks by end 2Q</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-government-deposits-rs1-1trillion-in-state-banks-by-end-2q-243679/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Economy Two]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 02:05:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fiscal]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243679</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka&#8217;s government has deposited 1.1 trillion rupees in state banks by end of the second quarter of 2025, a Financial Stability Report issued by the central bank has revealed.</p>
<p>&#8220;Of this, a significant share of 80.7 percent was concentrated in term deposits maturing within one year, while the remainder was maintained as on-demand,&#8221; the central bank said.</p>
<p>&#8220;The absence of deposits with maturities beyond one year highlights the short term nature of these balances. </p>
<p>&#8220;Although such deposits provide a substantial funding base for the banks, their maturity profile highlights potential liquidity risk in the event of sudden withdrawals driven by macroeconomic conditions.&#8221;</p>
<p>Sri Lanka has built a so-called &#8216;fiscal buffer&#8217; by overborrowing supposedly to control interest rates, as macro-economists running the Treasury tried to control fuel prices with a fund, and prevent the true effect of government cashflow need changes from being passed on to the economy to maintain the credit system in balance and reduce consumption.</p>
<p>In the run up to the policy errors by macro-economists that led to serial currency crises from 2015, a so-called &#8216;buffer strategy&#8217; has been identified as one of the culprits by critics. </p>
<p>The back-to-to back currency and stabilization crises, where aggressive open market operations were also involved, then led to the economic strategy of the so-called &#8216;Yahapalana regime&#8217; being discredited including within coalition partners as the currency depreciated, food and energy prices went up, and import controls were imposed.</p>
<p>RELATED</p>
<p><a href="https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-controls-imports-in-nixon-shock-move-to-protect-soft-pegged-rupee-11681/">Sri Lanka controls imports in ‘Nixon-shock’ move to protect soft-pegged rupee</a></p>
<p><a href="https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-president-calls-to-expand-nixon-shock-as-rupee-falls-11867/">Sri Lanka President calls to expand Nixon shock as rupee falls</a></p>
<p>When deposits in state banks financed by the over-issue of Treasury bills are re-lent to customers, banks then use central bank liquidity windows or term facilities to return cash to the Treasury, triggering forex shortages, currency pressure and fx reserve losses when the money is demanded back in large volumes.</p>
<p>The state is the largest customer of the banking system and its actions tend to have ripple effects across the credit system such as when interbank facilities are cut to return cash leading to window borrowings.</p>
<p>Analysts have pointed out that it is not possible to control interest rates by domestically invested &#8216;buffers&#8217; in the context of a central banks with a policy rate and it can only be done by an externally invested sovereign wealth fund as countries like Singapore do.</p>
<p>However, if state banks did not lend the money back to the government through Treasury bills or bonds or to interbank participants (which will lead to a spike in rates when the facilities are cut suddenly or lead to window borrowings) and instead kept as excess liquidity in the central bank, it could lead initially lead to an initial increase in forex reserves.</p>
<p>When the money is withdrawn by the Treasury, excess liquidity will drop, trigger pressure on the exchange as the money is used in the economy and reserve losses will take place, or the currency will be depreciated unless reserves are sold to mop up the extra liquidity.</p>
<p>There was no information on at what rates the 1.1 trillion rupees was raised, or whether it came from tax revenues while other securities were rolled over, and at what rates the money was deposited in state banks, which would indicate the loss or profit of the operation.</p>
<p>If the money was originally raised by selling bonds to banks, it is also not known whether banks again re-lent to the government at a lower rate on a shorter tenure. </p>
<p>Banks and other financial intermediaries in general make money (assuming markets are reasonably efficient) by borrowing short and lending long as much as their capital buffers permit. (Colombo/Oct12/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka Companies Act amendment marks a cultural shift: Panel</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-companies-act-amendment-marks-a-cultural-shift-panel-243672/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nirmalie Alahakone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2025 14:07:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Legal]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243672</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Deloitte webinar unpacks the Companies (Amendment) Act No. 12 of 2025]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Deloitte Sri Lanka hosted a webinar “Reforming Today for a Resilient Tomorrow: Understanding the Companies (Amendment) Act No. 12 of 2025” following the enactment of the landmark amendment to the Companies Act No. 7 of 2007 on 4th August 2025. </p>
<p>This amendment marks a significant step in strengthening Sri Lanka’s regulatory framework for corporates, with beneficial ownership disclosure as its key feature. </p>
<p>This webinar brought together corporate law experts, regulators, and Deloitte professionals to discuss how these reforms will reshape business practices, governance, and compliance.</p>
<p>Delivering the keynote, Dr. Harsha Cabral, President’s Counsel and Chairman of National Savings Bank, outlined the evolution of corporate law in Sri Lanka and the growing importance of transparency. </p>
<p>He highlighted that global bodies such as the Financial Action Task Force (FATF), World Bank, and United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC) have long called for identifying the real owners of corporate entities to prevent misuse of company structures for money laundering, tax evasion, and other illicit activities. </p>
<p>Many countries, including Sri Lanka, began introducing beneficial ownership declarations as early as 2018 through financial institutions, and with this new amendment Act these obligations are now formally mandated under corporate law. </p>
<p>Dr Cabral emphasised that this represents not just a legal update but a cultural shift, placing clear duties on directors, secretaries, and shareholders to ensure accountability and transparency.</p>
<p>Shivandini Liyanage, Senior Vice President – Legal Enforcement &amp; Compliance at the Colombo Stock Exchange (CSE), explained how the CSE is preparing to align its rules with the new requirements. </p>
<p>She noted that although regulations and prescribed forms are still to be finalised, the Central Depository Systems (CDS) must begin preparing now by establishing internal systems, issuing guidelines, and working closely with brokers and custodians to identify and report beneficial owners; particularly those holding 10% or more of shares. </p>
<p>Given the complexity of ownership structures, she stressed that both CDS and companies will need to strengthen due diligence processes, modernise data collection practices, and train staff to ensure compliance once the Act becomes fully operational.</p>
<p>From the regulatory perspective, Shyama Harshani, Registrar at the Registrar of Companies, detailed how the ROC will implement the new beneficial ownership disclosure regime. </p>
<p>She explained that companies will be required to file seven (7) key Beneficial Ownership (BO) forms (B01 to B07) on the eROC portal within prescribed timelines and with applicable fees, as to be set out in the upcoming regulations. </p>
<p>She ensured that all information will be stored in a centralised registry accessible to regulators and, with certain restrictions, to the public, reinforcing both transparency and compliance with anti-money laundering and corporate governance laws. </p>
<p>Harshani underlined that to avoid penalties, companies must keep pace with regulatory updates, submit reports on time, and maintain accurate BO records.</p>
<p>This session also introduced Deloitte’s Green BO Flow, a SharePoint-based automation process that digitalises and streamlines the collection of beneficial ownership details and securely maintains a beneficial ownership register. </p>
<p>By reducing manual effort and embedding ESG principles such as paperless processes and data privacy, Deloitte perceives compliance as a transparent and sustainable practice through Green BO Flow.</p>
<p>Moderating the panel discussion, Disna Perera, Director – Corporate Secretarial at Deloitte Sri Lanka, shared Deloitte’s perspective on turning compliance into an opportunity for stronger governance. She further emphasised “The message is clear &#8211; the bar for governance requirements has been raised. </p>
<p>Companies must quickly adapt to these changes and leverage technology effectively. </p>
<p>This is crucial not only to mitigate risks but also to ensure compliance with the evolving regulatory landscape”.</p>
<p>The webinar reaffirmed Deloitte’s role in helping corporates navigate regulatory reforms with confidence, providing practical insights and proactive tools to align compliance with long-term resilience.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Kapila Perera appointed secretary to Sri Lanka&#8217;s Ministry of Urban Development</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/kapila-perera-appointed-secretary-to-sri-lankas-ministry-of-urban-development-243669/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nirmalie Alahakone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2025 13:18:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Political News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243669</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Perera was previously the secretary to the Ministry of Transport, Highways, Ports and Civil Aviation.
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT &#8211; Kapila C K Perera has been appointed secretary to Sri Lanka&#8217;s Ministry of Transport, Highways and Urban Development, the president’s media division said.</p>
<p>Perera was previously the secretary to the Ministry of Transport, Highways, Ports and Civil Aviation.</p>
<p>On Thursday, president Anura Dissanayake removed minister Bimal Rathnayake&#8217;s Ports and Civil Aviation portfolios in a cabinet &#8216;reshuffle&#8217;. </p>
<p>Rathnayake was Minister of Transport, Highways, Ports and Civil Aviation. (Colombo/Oct11/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka August tourism revenue up 1-pct amid steep rise in arrivals</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-august-tourism-revenue-up-1-pct-amid-steep-rise-in-arrivals-243642/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shihar Aneez]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2025 11:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Tourism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243642</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Revenue fell year-on-year in the previous two months despite increase in arrivals]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka’s foreign exchange revenue from tourism in August 2025 edged up 1 percent from a year ago to 182.9 million US dollars, the central bank said, quoting tourism promotion authority data.</p>
<p>The monthly revenue showed a rise for the first time in three months. It has been falling in the last two straight months.</p>
<p>The revenue from tourism, which accounts for nearly 3 percent of the island nation’s economy, rose 1 percent, despite 30 percent increase in the monthly tourist arrivals, the data showed.</p>
<p>In July, the revenue fell 3 percent to 318.5 million US dollars compared to the same month in the previous year’s 328.3 million US dollars. In August, the revenue fell 8.2 percent from a year ago to 258.9 million US dollars.</p>
<p>The tourist arrivals saw a jump of 30.1 percent to 158,971 in September, the official data showed.</p>
<p>The revenue for the first nine months up to September has seen a rise of 5.3 percent to 2.47 billion US dollars from a year ago.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka’s new government has aimed at ambitious 5 billion US dollar revenue and a 3 million arrival target this year.</p>
<p>The island nation witnessed 3.17 billion dollar revenue in 2024, with a 53.2 percent jump compared to 2.07 billion dollars in the previous year, the data showed.</p>
<p>The arrivals also have picked up 16.3 percent in the first nine months of 2025 compared to the same period last year with the number of foreign visitors to Sri Lanka rising to 1,725,494 in the period compared to last year’s 1,484,808.</p>
<p>The arrivals jumped 38.1 percent to 2.05 million in 2024 compared to the previous year. Sri Lanka missed its ambitious 2.3 million tourist arrival target and 5 billion dollar revenue goal in 2024.</p>
<p>Tourism accounted for nearly 5 percent of Sri Lanka’s economy when the sector was at its peak in 2018. Since then, it has been hit by violent Easter Sunday suicide attack in 2019 and Covid-19 pandemic in 2020 followed by an unprecedented economic crisis.</p>
<p>The tourism earnings figure is estimated from a survey conducted by the Sri Lanka Tourism Development Authority.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka’s imports and the merchandise trade deficit have gradually picked up as tourism earnings came in and people in the sector spent the wages and other earnings. (Colombo/October 11/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Green cars, red light for Sri Lanka</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/green-cars-red-light-for-sri-lanka-243653/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Economy Two]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2025 06:14:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Op-ed/Special Reports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Opinion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243653</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[EV users contribute less to state coffers]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT &#8211; The flood of electric cars may be a dream come true for a well-heeled few, but do they really contribute to a cleaner environment or fill state coffers in the same way as other motorists?</p>
<p>Electric cars are more expensive than petrol, or diesel-powered vehicles, which means more foreign exchange leaves the country to import an electric vehicle (EV). </p>
<p>The tariff on an EV is also much lower than that on a fossil fuel-powered vehicle. As a result, the state earns far less tax revenue on every dollar spent to import an EV.</p>
<p>While the prohibitive 200 percent + tax on diesel and petrol vehicles is aimed at discouraging their import, the state derives the bulk of its revenue from them.</p>
<p><b>Cheap Electricity</b></p>
<p>EVs are marketed as a “greener” alternative, but this claim is questionable when considering how electricity is generated in Sri Lanka. </p>
<p>About half of the country’s daily electricity comes from coal and diesel oil as of October, though the number has been higher in some months.</p>
<p>Therefore, charging an EV from the national grid does not significantly reduce the environmental impact compared with using a conventional petrol or diesel car, also known as ICE or internal combustion engine vehicles. </p>
<p>Moreover, when an EV is charged from the grid, no taxes are paid, unlike at the petrol pump, where about half of the cost of petrol goes to the state as tax. Every time a motorist tops up their tank, they also top up state coffers. Not so with EVs. </p>
<p>If EV&#8217;s use commercial charging, some VAT is collected.</p>
<p><b>Solar Panels</b></p>
<p>EV owners argue that they use their own solar panels to charge their vehicles and thus place no burden on the national grid. Yes and no. Fast charging is not possible from a domestic charger. </p>
<p>Installing one’s own solar panel system involves a very high initial cost, meaning more foreign exchange is spent to import the necessary equipment. Those solar panels are imported tax-free. Once again, there is no direct benefit to the treasury. EV users solar-power generation is also subsidized. </p>
<p>Instead of focusing on the promotion of electric vehicles, Sri Lanka should improve public transport. Ideally, there should be more incentives, at least in the short term,  for petrol vehicles, as those motorists contribute to state revenue every time they drive, unlike EV owners.</p>
<p>While electric vehicles may offer certain advantages, they are not the ideal solution for Sri Lanka, certainly not while the national grid is largely dependent on coal and diesel. Sri Lanka is only shifting pollution from its roads to Norachcholai, Kelanitissa, Kerawalapitiya and a few other places where thermal generators are located.</p>
<p>The country should focus on developing sustainable public transport that benefits all citizens, not just the wealthy few driving EVs.</p>
<p><b>Firefighting</b></p>
<p>Another glaring deficiency is the lack of equipment or training for police, firefighters and paramedics to deal with accidents involving electric vehicles. Attending to an EV crash poses a high-voltage danger to passengers, pedestrians and first responders.</p>
<p>There is nothing in the public domain to suggest Sri Lanka’s traffic police are trained to deal with emergencies involving EVs or even hybrid vehicles. Countries such as Australia have recognised the need for specialised training to deal with EVs and have extensive programmes to educate first responders as well as the public. </p>
<p>Australia has a National Electric Vehicle Strategy, which includes training on how to handle EV incidents and high-voltage lithium-ion batteries, which also contain highly hazardous material.</p>
<p><b>Greenwashing </b></p>
<p>On a purely environmental note, there is no evidence that importers of EVs or hybrid vehicles have set up any facility for recycling the batteries of their vehicles. The requirement to have a battery recycling facility was initially a condition for allowing EV imports during the ban on other vehicle imports between 2020 and February this year. Again, there is no evidence to suggest that this condition was fulfilled. </p>
<p>In a few years, Sri Lanka could end up with a mountain of discarded EV batteries that will be a bigger hazard and threat to public safety than anything the country has had to deal with so far.</p>
<p><b>Level field</b></p>
<p>I am not arguing against EVs, but I oppose the special concessions they enjoy while others are taxed to the maximum, both at the time of import and during use. Considering the loss of revenue to the state from the operation of an EV, the electric vehicle road tax (annual licence) should be adjusted to recover this loss. </p>
<p>A previous government imposed a similar surcharge on diesel-powered vehicles used for non-commercial purposes. The argument then was that these vehicles, mostly vans, were using subsidised diesel and thereby causing a loss to the state. Now that diesel is no longer subsidised, that argument no longer holds. However, a similar tax could be applied to EVs.</p>
<p>The green argument for electric vehicles simply doesn&#8217;t hold up, given the subsidies continually granted to EV users, who contribute far less to state coffers than users of internal combustion engine vehicles. </p>
<p>These petrol heads should be seen as the true heroes in defending the economy and subsidising the green dreams of a wealthy few.</p>
<p>(The writer is a regular user of public transport who switched to his own three-wheeler over two decades ago)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka private credit expands Rs226.8bn in August 2025 in new record</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-private-credit-expands-rs226-8bn-in-august-2025-in-new-record-243625/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Economy Two]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2025 02:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Finance]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243625</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Credit to government falls]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT  &#8211; Sri Lanka&#8217;s private credit hit a new record of 226.8 billion rupees in August 2025, up from 201.5 billion rupees a month earlier, taking the total so in 2025 to 1,128 billion rupees, while credit to government fell, official data shows.</p>
<p>Sri Lanka&#8217;s central bank has provided monetary stability as it missed an inflation target, allowing people  &#8211; including many who were starving and forced to skip meals after macroeconomists steeply depreciated the currency in 2022 destroying real wages  &#8211; to slowly to pick up their lives, buying goods and allowing demand to recover and giving confidence for businesses to invest.</p>
<p>The private credit number only exceeded 226 billion rupees level in March 2022 when the macro-economists busted the currency in a &#8216;float&#8217; failed by a surrender rule, bloating outstanding dollar debt and working capital needs.</p>
<p>Vehicle imports are also picking up now, driving up credit. Many people are taking loans to pay taxes to the state, amid extraordinarily high levies for vehicles, including for motorcycles. </p>
<p>RELATED : <a href="https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-consumption-loans-driven-by-140-pct-surge-in-vehicle-loans-243524/">Sri Lanka consumption loans driven by 140-pct surge in vehicle loans</a></p>
<p>After deploying open market operations against the people in 2020, macro-economists banned car imports, hitting tax revenues in what analysts call a &#8216;cascading policy error&#8217;, often seen after rate cuts during earlier currency crises.</p>
<p>Banks also have credit lines to finance companies, and it is not clear whether those are also being activated, helping drive up private credit.</p>
<p>Credit to private sector grew to 9,284 billion rupees up to August, up 20.5 percent from a year ago, with domestic banking unit credit up 21.9 percent to 8,688.3 billion rupees and overseas banking units up 3 percent to, 608.5 billion rupees.</p>
<p>Net credit to government from commercial banks fell 165 billion rupees in August 2025, to 6,519 billion rupees. </p>
<p>For the month of August 2025 the government ran an overall budget surplus of around 145 billion rupees, data show.</p>
<p>In the year to August net credit to government grew only 4 percent.</p>
<p>With no inflation, current spending can also be kept under control and nominal interest rates can also eventually fall as long as the central bank does not cut rates artificially with inflationary open market operations or depreciates the currency for wanton inflationism, destroying savings and capital of the nation, analysts say.</p>
<p>There has been insidious depreciation in recent months amid record external current account surpluses, for reasons that are not clear, but probably to meet the controversial inflation floor of the central bank which will push up the cost of living, state expenditure and can help fire new social unrest.</p>
<p>There have been calls for the parliament to impose an inflation ceiling on the central bank to de-risk the economy from aggravated inflationism and prevent a second default that usually happens to countries that default the first time unless sound money is restored.</p>
<p>Credit to state enterprises grew 14.2 billion rupees, after falling 33 billion rupees in the previous month.</p>
<p>By debasing money through insidious depreciation, inflationist macro-economists can also push up costs of state energy enterprises put pressure on their balance sheets, eventually raising selling prices and pressure especially incomes of families, especially in marginal income brackets. (Colombo/Oct11/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka President appoints Maithri Wickremesinghe to Central Bank’s Governing Board</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-president-appoints-maithri-wickremesinghe-to-central-banks-governing-board-243622/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shihar Aneez]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 15:23:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Monetary]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243622</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[He will be a member of the Central Bank's Monetary Board as well]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id=":nu" class="Am aiL Al editable LW-avf tS-tW tS-tY" tabindex="1" role="textbox" contenteditable="true" spellcheck="false" aria-label="Message Body" aria-multiline="true" aria-owns=":tw" aria-controls=":tw" aria-expanded="false">
<p class="gmail-MsoListParagraphCxSpMiddle">ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka President Anura Kumara Dissanayake has appointed President&#8217;s Councel Maithri Evan Wickremesinghe as the new member of the Central Bank’s Governing Board after Rajeev Amarasuriya, the current President of the country’s Bar Association relinquished from his duties as a member from June this year.</p>
<p class="gmail-MsoListParagraphCxSpMiddle">Wickremesinghe’s appointment has been effective from October 2, the Central Bank said in a statement.</p>
<p class="gmail-MsoListParagraphCxSpMiddle">Wickremesinghe is a Fellow of the Chartered Institute of Management Accountants (UK) and holds an Honours Degree in Law from the University of Colombo.</p>
<p class="gmail-MsoListParagraphCxSpMiddle">He is a practicing lawyer appearing as a counsel in the appellate courts of Sri Lanka and at arbitrations both at national and international levels.</p>
<p class="gmail-MsoListParagraphCxSpMiddle">He also functions as an arbitrator in national and international arbitrations and has been an expert witness on Sri Lankan law for litigations overseas.</p>
<p class="gmail-MsoListParagraphCxSpMiddle">Wickremesinghe had previously held the positions of a Senior Independent Director of Nations Trust Bank and the Chairman of its Audit Review Committee and the Nominations Committee.</p>
<p class="gmail-MsoListParagraphCxSpMiddle">He was also an Independent Director of Hemas Holdings Plc and the Chairman of its Audit Committee and a member of the Remuneration Committee.</p>
<p class="gmail-MsoListParagraphCxSpMiddle">The Governing Board has been established as the body responsible for overseeing the administration and management of the affairs of the Central Bank and determination of its general policies.</p>
<p class="gmail-MsoListParagraphCxSpLast">The members of the Governing Board will be members of the Monetary Policy Board as well. (Colombo/October 10/2025)</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka worker remittances up 25.2-pct in September 2025</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-worker-remittances-up-25-2-pct-in-september-2025-243619/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shihar Aneez]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 14:34:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Economy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243619</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Remittances are one of Sri Lanka's top foreign exchange earners ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka’s official remittances rose 25.2 percent to 695.7 million dollars in September 2025, while the total in the first nine months reached 5.81 billion dollars rising 20 percent from a year ago, central bank data showed, with more people leaving to work abroad.</p>
<p>The worker remittances hit a six-year high in 2024 after a record number from the island nation’s labour force left the country searching for foreign jobs amid Sri Lanka’s recovery from an unprecedented economic crisis, official data showed.</p>
<p>In 2024 full year remittances rose 10.1 percent to 6.57 billion dollars, from nearly 6 billion in the previous year, the Central Bank data showed.</p>
<p>Worker remittances are one of the top foreign exchange revenue earners for the island nation which is still recovering from an unprecedented economic crisis hit in 2022.</p>
<p>The remittances have risen continuously after the central bank gave up a parallel exchange rate regime, which compelled most expatriates to switch informal Undiyal and Hawala money transfer methods.</p>
<p>The island nation has been in the process of sending more migrant workers focusing on professionals to bring in higher foreign exchange since the country declared bankruptcy in 2022.</p>
<p>The Sri Lanka Bureau of Foreign Employment (SLBFE) reports that 212,302 Sri Lankans left for overseas jobs between January and August 2025.</p>
<p>A total of 212,302 Sri Lankans have gone abroad for employment during the first eight months of 2025, the official data from Sri Lanka Bureau of Foreign Employment (SLBFE) showed.</p>
<p>Worker remittances coming through official channels fell sharply in 2021 after many expatriates switched to informal money transferring channels as they were given higher rates than formal banking channels.</p>
<p>The move came after the Central Bank printed to sterilize interventions and keep a policy rate down, triggering parallel exchange rates, which were settled outside the formal banking system.</p>
<p>From April 2022, the interest rates were raised by unprecedented levels, slowing credit and the need to print money to keep rates down. Later, the Central Bank started its dovish monetary policy. (Colombo/October 10/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka rupee stronger against dollar, bond yields slightly down intra day</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-rupee-stronger-against-dollar-bond-yields-slightly-down-intra-day-243613/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nirmalie Alahakone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 11:30:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Bonds & Forex]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243613</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Bond yields recovered at close, dealers said.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka’s rupee closed at 302.60/68 to the US dollar on Friday, stronger from 302.75/83 the previous day, while bond yields recovered at close, dealers said.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.03.2028 closed at 9.10/20 percent, from 9.11/15 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.09.2029 closed at 9.67/72 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.05.2030 closed at 9.77/80 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.03.2031 closed at 10.08/12 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.12.2032 closed at 10.50/60 percent, from 10.48/60 percent. (Colombo/Oct10/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka stocks close up as positive sentiment continues</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-stocks-close-up-as-positive-sentiment-continues-243605/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nirmalie Alahakone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 09:57:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Stocks & Companies]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243605</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Turnover was 8.45 billion rupees, above the monthly average of 7 billion rupees.
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT &#8211; Sri Lanka&#8217;s Colombo Stock Exchange closed up on Friday, as positive sentiment in the market continued, brokers said.</p>
<p>&#8220;There&#8217;s a couple of reasons for this; one is that with the low interest rates limiting alternative investments there is new money coming in to the market,&#8221; Ranjan Ranatunga, Assistant Vice President – Research at First Capital said.</p>
<p>&#8220;And then of course sentiment is getting better with the IMF announcement.&#8221;</p>
<p>The All Share Price Index closed up 0.65 percent, or 143.98 points, at 22,318.72; while the S&#038;P SL20 closed up  1.17 percent, or 71.95 points, at 6,234.33.</p>
<p>Turnover was 8.45 billion rupees, above the monthly average of 7 billion rupees.</p>
<p>A crossing on Mercantile Investments and Finance contributed 990 million rupees to this. The share closed flat at 2,600 rupees.</p>
<p>&#8220;We saw a shift in interest from small caps to heavy weights like Commecial Bank (up 1.75 rupees at 205) and John Keells Holdings (up 90 cents at 21.80 rupees).&#8221;</p>
<p>There was also interest in cables stocks after a subdivision, he said. (Colombo/Oct10/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka&#8217;s Laugfs Dubai unit named by US Treasury for trading Iran gas</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lankas-laugfs-dubai-unit-named-by-us-treasury-for-trading-iran-gas-243591/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Economy Two]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 06:55:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Petroleum]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243591</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Alleges Iran gas was delivered to Sri Lanka and Bangladesh]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – The United States Department of the Treasury’s Office of Foreign Assets Control (OFAC) has named Slogal Energy DMCC, a unit of Sri Lanka&#8217;s Laugfs group, for alledgedly trading in Iranian petrochemicals.</p>
<p>&#8220;United Arab Emirates (UAE)-based Markan White Trading Crude Oil Abroad Co. L.L.C (Markan White) and Slogal Energy DMCC (Slogal) play a key role in enabling the sale and shipment of Iranian LPG to Sri Lanka,&#8221; a <a href="https://home.treasury.gov/news/press-releases/sb0275">US Treasury statement</a> said.</p>
<p>Iranian petrochemicals had been purchased from Iran-based petrochemical broker Persian Gulf Petrochemical Industry Commercial Co (PGPICC) by Dubai based firms.</p>
<p>&#8220;In late 2024, PGPICC and Markan White used Slogal to help facilitate the sale, shipment, and export of millions of dollars’ worth of Iranian LPG to Sri Lanka,&#8221; the report said.</p>
<p>&#8220;In 2024 and 2025, Slogal purchased Iranian LPG that was delivered to Sri Lanka, with multiple shipments of Iranian LPG reaching end users in Sri Lanka and Bangladesh.  </p>
<p>&#8220;In 2024, Palau-flagged MAX STAR (IMO9134165) delivered Iranian LPG that was purchased by Slogal.  Similarly in 2025, Slogal purchased Iranian LPG that was delivered by Panama-flagged GAS DIOR (IMO 9379404) to Sri Lanka.  </p>
<p>&#8220;In early 2025, GAS DIOR delivered over 17,000 metric tons of Iranian LPG to Bangladesh, making an additional LPG delivery for now-sanctioned supplier Octane Energy FZCO. &#8221;</p>
<p>Slogal Energy DMCC, along with several Chinese and UAE firms were were &#8220;designated pursuant to Executive Orer 13902 for operating in the petroleum sector of the Iranian economy,&#8221; the American statement said.</p>
<p>Several individuals including Indians, were named as blocked persons.</p>
<p>&#8220;As a result of today’s action, all property and interests in property of the designated or blocked persons described above that are in the United States or in the possession or control of U.S. persons are blocked and must be reported to OFAC,&#8221; the statement said.</p>
<p>&#8220;In addition, any entities that are owned, directly or indirectly, individually or in the aggregate, 50 percent or more by one or more blocked persons are also blocked.  </p>
<p>&#8220;Unless authorized by a general or specific license issued by OFAC, or exempt, OFAC’s regulations generally prohibit all transactions by U.S. persons or within (or transiting) the United States that involve any property or interests in property of blocked persons. </p>
<p>&#8220;Violations of U.S. sanctions may result in the imposition of civil or criminal penalties on U.S. and foreign persons.  OFAC may impose civil penalties for sanctions violations on a strict liability basis.  </p>
<p>&#8220;In addition, financial institutions and other persons may risk exposure to sanctions for engaging in certain transactions or activities involving designated or otherwise blocked persons.  </p>
<p>&#8220;The prohibitions include the making of any contribution or provision of funds, goods, or services by, to, or for the benefit of any designated or blocked person, or the receipt of any contribution or provision of funds, goods, or services from any such person.&#8221; (Colombo/Oct10/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>UN mission, Sri Lanka officials discuss strengthening electoral processes</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/un-mission-sri-lanka-officials-discuss-strengthening-electoral-processes-243574/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nirmalie Alahakone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 06:39:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Elections]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243574</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[UN Technical Electoral Needs Assessment Mission meets key Parliament members]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT &#8211; A team from the UN Technical Electoral Needs Assessment Mission has met key parliament members, including prime minister Harini Amarasuriya and opposition leader Sajith Premadasa, to assess opportunities for international support to strengthen electoral processes in Sri Lanka.</p>
<p>&#8220;The mission focused on gathering insights from a wide range of stakeholders including government representatives, political parties, election observers, civil society, and development partners,&#8221; parliament statement said.</p>
<p>&#8220;Discussions centered on enhancing the efficiency, transparency, and inclusivity of Sri Lanka’s electoral system.&#8221;</p>
<p>Key topics addressed included strengthening transparency and integrity in elections, increasing women&#8217;s political representation, promoting political literacy and voter education, advancing the digitalization of the electoral process, empowering voters, protecting voting rights, and tackling challenges faced by youth and women in politics.</p>
<p>The United Nations delegation expressed the UN’s willingness to extend technical assistance to support ongoing and future electoral reforms.</p>
<p>The delegation comprised Michele Griffin, Director of the Electoral Assistance Division; Dan Malinovich, Electoral Policy Specialist; Amanda Stark, Political Affairs Officer in the Asia and the Pacific Division; and Mikyong Kim, Political/Electoral Affairs Officer. (Colombo/Oct10/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka’s People’s Leasing &#038; Finance lists new shares after scrip dividend</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lankas-peoples-leasing-finance-lists-new-shares-after-scrip-dividend-243570/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nirmalie Alahakone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 06:17:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Stocks & Companies]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243570</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[55,491,496 ordinary voting shares of the Company have been listed with effect from 10 October ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka’s People’s Leasing &#038; Finance said it has listed  55,491,496 new ordinary voting shares after a scrip dividend.</p>
<p>“Please note that 55,491,496 ordinary voting shares of the Company have been listed with effect from 10th October 2025, pursuant to a Scrip Dividend,” the bank said in stock exchange <a href="https://cdn.cse.lk/cmt/announcement_portal_prod/Notification%20on%20the%20Listing%20of%20Shares_33860522915820115.pdf" target="_blank">filing</a>.</p>
<p>The stock was trading down 40 cents at 27.70 rupees on Friday. (Colombo/Oct10/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka consumption loans driven by 140-pct surge in vehicle loans</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-consumption-loans-driven-by-140-pct-surge-in-vehicle-loans-243524/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Economy Two]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 05:16:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Finance]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243524</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Personal loans grew by 25.3 percent]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka&#8217;s consumption loans, the largest credit segment in the banking sector totaling 2.3 trillion rupees, grew 11 percent in the year to the June 2025 quarter, driven by vehicle credits, the central bank said in a <a href="https://www.cbsl.gov.lk/sites/default/files/cbslweb_documents/publications/fssr/fsr_2025e.pdf">Financial Stability Report</a>.</p>
<p>Leasing and hire purchase facilities grew 140.5 percent by end 2Q, after import controls were relaxed in February 2025.</p>
<p>Vehicle loans are considered &#8216;consumption&#8217; though the asset have long lives, high second hand values, especially in Sri Lanka, when currencies are busted by macro-economists and may improve productivity by cutting down transport times and generate income. </p>
<p>Personal loans grew by 25.3 percent, while pawning and credit card portfolios also expanded, the report said.</p>
<p>State 3 bad loans of consumption loans were 4.0 percent by end June from 5.0 percent last year.</p>
<p>Credit to construction sector, made up of 14.5 percent of the total, grew 14.8 percent in the year to June 2014 compared to contraction of 8.2 percent last year.</p>
<p>After macro-economist fire unsustainable credit from rate cuts and open market operations, property is one of the sectors that gets most badly hit, as the bubble deflates later.</p>
<p>In countries with reserve collecting central banks, building materials imports also surge, generating forex shortages and triggering a currency crisis. (Colombo/Oct10/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka appoints new ministers for aviation and ports, water supply</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-appoints-new-ministers-for-aviation-and-ports-water-supply-243535/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nirmalie Alahakone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 04:42:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Parliament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Political News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243535</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A Sri Lanka Cabinet 'reshuffle' has seen Anura Karunathilaka appointed Minister of Ports and Civil Aviation]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT &#8211; A Sri Lanka Cabinet &#8216;reshuffle&#8217; has seen <a href="https://www.parliament.lk/members-of-parliament/directory-of-past-members/viewMember/3604" target="_blank">Anura Karunathilaka</a> appointed Minister of Ports and Civil Aviation, and <a href="https://www.parliament.lk/en/component/members/viewMember/3568?Itemid=206" target="_blank">H M Susil Ranasinghe</a> appointed Minister of Housing, Construction and Water Supply.</p>
<p>Bimal Ratnayake is now Minister of Transport, Highways and Urban Development, according to a government statement. He was Minister of Transport, Highways, Ports and Civil Aviation.</p>
<p>Anil Jayantha Fernando is Deputy Minister of Finance and Planning.</p>
<p>Karunathilaka was formerly Minister of Urban Development, Construction and Housing, and Ranasinghe was Deputy Minister of Land and Irrigation.</p>
<p>T B Sarath &#8211; Deputy Minister of Housing, Construction and Water Supply (former Deputy Minister of Housing)<br />
M M Mohamed Munir &#8211; Deputy Minister of Religious and Cultural Affairs (former Deputy Minister of National Integration)<br />
Eranga Gunasekara &#8211; Deputy Minister of Urban Development (former Deputy Minister of Youth Affairs)<br />
Hansaka Wijayamuni &#8211; Deputy Minister of Health (Deputy Minister of Health and Mass Media)<br />
Aravinda Senarath Vitarana &#8211; Deputy Minister of Lands and Irrigation<br />
Dinindu Saman Kumara &#8211; Deputy Minister of Youth Affairs<br />
Nishantha Jayaweera &#8211; Deputy Minister of Economic Development<br />
Kaushalya Ariyarathne &#8211; Deputy Minister of Mass Media<br />
M I M Arkam &#8211; Deputy Minister of Energy<br />
(Colombo/Oct10/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka rupee flat against dollar, bond yields steady</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-rupee-flat-against-dollar-bond-yields-steady-243525/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nirmalie Alahakone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 04:13:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Bonds & Forex]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243525</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Stocks were trading up]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka’s rupee opened at 302.70/80 to the US dollar on Friday, slightly stronger from 302.75/83 the previous day, while bond yields were broadly steady, dealers said.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.03.2028 was quoted at 9.10/18 percent, up from 9.11/15 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 01.09.2028 was quoted at 9.20/30 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.10.2029 was quoted at 9.73/75 percent, up from 9.71/75 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.12.2029 was quoted at 9.73/75 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 01.07.2030 was quoted at 9.75/85 percent, from 9.77/81 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.03.2031 was quoted at 10.05/18 percent.</p>
<p>A bond maturing on 15.12.2032 was quoted at 10.50/65 percent, down from 10.48/60 percent. </p>
<p>The telegraphic transfer rates for the American dollar was 299.2500 buying, 306.2500 selling; the British pound was 397.2146 buying, and 408.5764 selling, and the euro was 343.9087 buying, 355.2719 selling.</p>
<p>The Colombo Stocks Exchange was trading in green; The ASPI was up 0.23 percent, or 49.93 points, at 22,224.67; the S&#038;P SL20 was down 0.15 percent, or 9.42 points, at 6,171.80. (Colombo/Oct10/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka&#8217;s HNB helps finance syndicated loan for Singapore energy firm</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lankas-hnb-helps-finance-syndicated-loan-for-singapore-energy-firm-243512/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Economy Two]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 02:41:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Finance]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243512</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka&#8217;s Hatton National Bank said it had participated in a billion dollar sustainability-linked syndicated term loan for Singapore-based Aster Chemicals &#038; Energy Pte Ltd.</p>
<p>DBS Bank and Oversea-Chinese Banking Corporation Limited (OCBC) served as mandated lead arrangers, underwriters, and bookrunners, and as sustainability coordinators, the bank said.</p>
<p>&#8220;This transaction reflects HNB’s strategic ambition to drive high-impact, cross-border financing that supports global sustainability goals,&#8221; HNB, Senior Vice President and Head of Corporate Banking, Manojith Weerasuriya said in a statement.</p>
<p>&#8220;Partnering with leading international institutions strengthens our commitment to creating lasting value through responsible banking and innovative financial solutions.&#8221;</p>
<p>Aster, Chemicals &#038; Energy is a joint venture majority-owned by Chandra Asri Group with Glencore as the minority partner, HNB said.  It runs a crude oil refinery and ethylene cracker in Pulau Bukom, together with downstream chemical facilities in Jurong Island.</p>
<p>The proceeds from the facility are linked to reductions in greenhouse gas emissions intensity, and will be used for general corporate purposes, including rejuvenation projects for Aster’s assets on Pulau Bukom and Jurong Island. </p>
<p>&#8220;Our participation in this landmark transaction underscores HNB’s deep commitment to fostering sustainable and responsible financing,&#8221; HNB, Senior Vice President / Head of Wholesale Banking Majella Rodrigo said in a statement.</p>
<p>&#8220;We take pride in joining hands with our global partners to champion sustainability linked initiatives that strengthen both environmental stewardship and long-term economic resilience.&#8221;</p>
<p>The volumes of HNB&#8217;s subcription was not disclosed.</p>
<p>Participating lenders in the syndicated loan included Clifford Capital, Mizuho Bank Ltd., PT Bank Mandiri (Persero) Tbk, PT Bank Negara Indonesia (Persero) Tbk, Singapore Branch, PT Bank Rakyat Indonesia (Persero) Tbk, Singapore Branch, Bangkok Bank PCL, First Abu Dhabi Bank PJSC (FAB), Indonesia Eximbank and Standard Chartered Bank. </p>
<p>The original 700 million dollar facility was upsized to 1,000 million dollars after oversubscription, HNB said. (Colombo/Oct09/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka in discussion with ADB for SME venture capital fund: official</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-in-discussion-with-adb-for-sme-venture-capital-fund-official-243492/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shihar Aneez]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 13:21:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Economy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243492</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[SME sector has been long facing lack of access for finance in Sri Lanka]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="font-weight: 400;">ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lankan authorities are in discussion with the Asian Development Bank to establish a venture capital fund to grant cheap finance access for the island nation’s small and medium sector enterprises (SME), a top official said.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">Manjula Hettiarachchi, Director General of the Department of Development Finance at the country’s Ministry of Finance said, if the discussions succeed, the country will have a venture capital fund from the next year.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">“Access to the finance for the SME sector has been a real issue with some commercial banks also hesitant to provide loans. We at the Finance Ministry have developed some schemes for those SMEs and we want them to access,” Hettiarachchi said during a discussion on Wednesday (08).</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">“We are at the initial stage of discussion with the ADB for this venture capital fund for SMEs.”</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">Sri Lanka’s SME sector forms the backbone of the national economy, accounting for over 75% of all businesses, more than 45% of employment, and contributing around 52% to the country’s GDP, according to the Ministry of Industry.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">Despite its vital role, the sector continues to struggle with limited access to finance, a major barrier to growth and innovation.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">Many SMEs lack formal financial records, collateral, or credit histories, factors that make traditional banks reluctant to lend.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">High interest rates, complex loan procedures, and stringent collateral requirements have further restricted borrowing capacity, particularly for rural entrepreneurs and women-led enterprises.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">The 2022 economic crisis and tightening monetary policy since 2022 have also worsened liquidity constraints, leading to reduced lending and delayed loan disbursements.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">As a result, thousands of SMEs remain trapped in a cycle of underinvestment, unable to expand operations, adopt technology, or enter export markets despite being the key drivers of job creation and inclusive growth in Sri Lanka. (Colombo/October 09/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>IMF needs Sri Lanka’s budget parameters to be in line with EFF for next disbursement</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/imf-needs-sri-lankas-budget-parameters-to-be-in-line-with-eff-for-next-disbursement-243493/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shihar Aneez]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 12:53:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243493</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[IMF has already disbursed USD 1.65 billion in five tranches]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="font-weight: 400;">ECONOMYNEXT – The International Monetary Fund wants Sri Lanka’s upcoming 2026 budget parameters to be in line with its External Fund Facility (EFF) programme as the prior action before the global lender’s board approving the Staff Level Agreement with the island nation’s authorities, a top official said.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">IMF staff and the Sri Lankan authorities have reached staff-level agreement on the country’s economic policies to conclude the Fifth Review of Sri Lanka’s reform program supported by the EFF.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">Once the review is approved by the IMF Executive Board, Sri Lanka will have access to about US$347 million in financing. However, Sri Lanka has to accomplish a prior action.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">“We have one prior this time. It is about the budget. And it is about ensuring that the budget parameters are in line with our program,” Evan Papageorgiou, the IMF Mission Chief for Sri Lanka told reporters at a media briefing after 15-day discussions with authorities.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">The parameters include a primary fiscal surplus target of 2.3 percent of the GDP.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">“Along side with that, we&#8217;re also judging the quality of the spending problems that are going to the budget. And this is something we have had a lot of discussions with the authorities, and we are keen and continue engaging with that,” Papageorgiou said.</p>
<p style="font-weight: 400;">If Sri Lanka complies with the expected prior action, the global lender will disburse the sixth tranche of the USD3 billion EFF. Already Sri Lanka has received around USD1.65 billion in the first five tranches. (Colombo/October 09/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sri Lanka sells extra Rs1.3bn Treasury bills after auction</title>
		<link>https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-sells-extra-rs1-3bn-treasury-bills-after-auction-243466/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nirmalie Alahakone]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 12:17:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Bonds & Forex]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://economynext.com/?p=243466</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Bringing the total of bills sold this week to 20.42 billion rupees.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ECONOMYNEXT – Sri Lanka has sold 1,300 million rupees of treasury bills offered on tap at average rates of 7.52 percent and 8.02 percent, the state debt office said, bringing the total of bills sold this week to 20.42 billion rupees.</p>
<p>The debt office sold 3-month bills at 7.52 percent.</p>
<p>The debt office sold 12-month bills at 8.02 percent.</p>
<p>On Wednesday (8) the debt office raised 19.12 billion rupees of 3, 6 and 12 month bills.</p>
<p><strong>Read more</strong><br />
<a href="https://economynext.com/sri-lanka-sells-67-pct-of-offered-bills-at-auction-rates-fixed-243329/#modal-one" target="_blank">Sri Lanka sells 67-pct of offered bills at auction, rates fixed</a></p>
<p>The date of settlement is October 10. (Colombo/Oct9/2025)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
